窈窕淑女
主演：奥黛丽 赫本
雷克斯 哈里逊
编剧：亚兰 艾勒纳
制片：杰克 华纳
导演：乔治 库克
太精彩了
WOMAN: Splendid.
抱歉 先生 我车上已经有客人了
VALET 1 : Sorry, sir, I've already got one there.
[CHATTERlNG]
过来 先生 过来
VALET 1 : Over here, sir, over here.
过来
VALET 2: Coming through.
[VALET 2 WHlSTLES]
过来 先生
VALET 1 : Over here, sir.
让下路
VALET 1 : Make way.
弗瑞迪 噢 已经太晚了
ELlZA: Freddy, oh, it's already very late.
[CHATTERlNG]
[PEOPLE MURMURlNG]
把它展开 赶紧盖好
MAN: Move it, darn it.
[HORN HONKlNG]
弗瑞迪 去叫辆马车来
[MRS. EYNSFORD-HILL] Freddy, go and find a cab.
你想让我得肺炎吗？
Do you want me to catch pneumonia?
当心点儿 笨蛋
MAN: Watch out, daffy.
他居然叫我是笨蛋
[lN COCKNEY ACCENT] He calls me a daffy.
别光站在那儿 弗瑞迪 去叫辆出租车来
Don't just stand there, Freddy. Go and find a cab.
好的 我这就去叫 我这就去叫车
All right, l'll get it. l'll get it.
我都被淋湿了
MAN: l'm getting wet.
[FREDDY WHlSTLES]
抱歉
MAN: l'm so sorry.
[GRUNTS]
走路要看路 先生 走路要看路啊
Look where you're going, dear. Look where you're going.
真是太抱歉了
l'm so sorry.
两束紫罗兰掉进泥水里了
Two bunches of violets trod in the mud.
这可是一天的收入
A full day's wages.
弗瑞迪
EYNSFORD-HlLL: Freddy.
弗瑞迪 还不快去叫辆出租车
Freddy, go and find a cab.
好的 妈妈
Yes, Mother.
噢 他是你儿子 对吧？
Oh, he's your son, is he?
噢 您要是愿意像一位母亲应该做的那样替他赔我
Well, if you'd done your duty by him as a mother should,
你可不能任他就这样糟蹋了一个可怜女孩儿的花儿
you wouldn't let him spoil a poor girl's flowers
却什么都不赔就这么跑了啊
and then run away without paying.
噢 接着做自己的生意去吧 姑娘
Oh, go about your business, my girl.
要是你不赔钱那就别想离开这儿
And you wouldn't go off without paying either.
有两束紫罗兰掉进泥水里了
Two bunches of violets trod in the mud.
我的天
Good heavens.
- 先生 您看这雨像是要停了吗？ - 我恐怕还要下
- Sir, is there any sign of it stopping? - I'm afraid not.
- 现在越下越大了 - 噢 天哪
- It's worse than before. - Oh, dear.
如果越下越大的话 那就表示雨快停了
lf it's worse, it's a sign it's nearly over.
高兴点吧 上校 买一束可怜女孩儿的花吧
Cheer up, captain. Buy a flower off a poor girl.
抱歉 我没零钱
l'm sorry, l haven't any change.
噢 半克朗我还是能找开的 给 这只要2便士 [克朗 英国旧币单位 =0.25镑=5先令=60便士 ]
Oh, l can change half a crown. Here, take this for tuppence.
我已经说了 非常抱歉 我没有...
l told you, l'm awfully sorry, l haven't--
噢 等等 噢 找到了
Oh, wait a minute. Oh, yes.
这儿有三个1便士的硬币 给你吧
Here's three ha'pence, if that's any use to you.
谢谢您 先生
Thank you, sir.
听着 你得当心点儿 收了钱最好给他一朵花
Here, you be careful. Better give him a flower for it.
在那柱子后边有个家伙
There is a bloke here behind that pillar
把你说的每句话都记下了
taking down every blessed word you're saying.
我同一位绅士说话又不算做了什么错事
l ain't done nothing wrong by speaking to the gentleman.
我有权在街边卖花
l've a right to sell flowers if l keep off the curb.
我可是个品行端正的女孩儿 请大家帮帮我
l'm a respectable girl, so help me.
我除了求他从我这里买一朵花儿之外再没说别的
l never spoke to him except to ask him to buy a flower off me.
- 别再说了 - 怎么这么吵？
MAN 1 : Don't start. - What's all the noise?
好像有个侦探要抓他
There's a tec taking her down.
我靠双手正直的生活着
l'm making an honest living.
是谁在那儿大喊大叫的？
MAN 2: Who's doing all that shouting?
- 这是怎么回事？ - 嗯...
- Where is it coming from? ELlZA: Well...
噢 先生 别让他控告我 他们不知道那对我意味着什么
Oh, sir, don't let him charge me. They don't know what it means to me.
他们会毁掉我的名誉让我流落街头…
They'll take away me character and drive me on the streets
只因为我同一位绅士说了话
for speaking to gentlemen.
慢着 慢着 慢着
There, there, there.
谁要伤害你 你这个傻女孩儿？你把我当成什么人了？
Who's hurting you, you silly girl? What you take me for?
我向圣经起誓 我一个字儿也没说过
On my Bible oath, l never spoke a word.
闭嘴 别说了 我看上去像是警察吗？
Shut up. Do l look like a policeman?
那你干嘛记下我说的话？
Then what did you take down me words for?
我怎么知道你有没有乱写呢？
How do l know you took me down right?
让我看看你都是怎么记的
You just show me what you wrote about me.
噢
ELlZA: Oh.
这是什么？这根本就是不正常的字
What's that? That ain't proper writing.
- 我看不懂 - 我可以
- I can't read it. - I can.
“我说 上校 请买一束可怜女孩儿的花吧”
"l say, captain, now buy a flower off a poor girl."
噢 就因为我叫了他“上校”
Oh, it's because l called him "captain."
哦 我没有冒犯的意思
Oh, l meant no harm.
先生 求您不要让他就因为那样一个词就控告我
Sir, don't let him lay a charge against me for a word like that.
我不会指控的
l'll make no charge.
真的吗 先生 如果你是位侦探 你没必要保护我
Really, sir, if you are a detective, you needn't begin protecting me
免受一位年轻女士的骚扰 除非我要求你那样做
against molestation from young women until l ask you.
谁都知道这个女孩没有恶意
Anyone could tell the girl meant no harm.
他可不是什么侦探 他是位绅士
He ain't no tec. He's a gentleman.
看他穿的靴子
Look at his boots.
你们都是从塞尔西来的吧？
How are all your people down at Selsey?
谁跟你说我们是从塞尔西来的？
Who told you my people come from Selsey?
别介意 但他们确实 告诉 我了
Never mind. They do.
你怎么会到东面这么远的地方来？
How do you come to be up so far east?
你出生在里森 格鲁夫吧
You were born in Lisson Grove.
噢 我离开里森 格鲁夫又怎么不对了？
Oh, what harm is there my leaving Lisson Grove?
那儿甚至连猪都住不下去 而且每周我都得花4到6镑？？
lt weren't fit for a pig to live in and l had to pay 4 and 6 a week--
随便你住哪儿 可不要再大吵大嚷了
Live where you like, but stop that noise.
行了 行了 他不会抓你了 你有权住在自己想待的地方
Come, come, he can't touch you. You've a right to live where you please.
- 我是个品行端正的女孩儿 我是认真的 - 是的 没错 没错
- I'm a good girl, l am. - Yes, yes, yes.
说下我是从哪儿来的？
Where do l come from?
豪斯敦 [英国城市]
Hoxton.
噢 谁说不是呢？ 啊 你什么都知道啊 说得一点没错
Well, who said l didn't? Blimey, you know everything, you do.
这位先生 你能替我叫一辆出租车吗？
You, sir, do you think you could find me a taxi?
不知道你有没有注意到 雨已经停了
l don't know whether you've noticed, but it's stopped raining.
你可以搭乘一辆去汉普顿法院的公共汽车
You can get a motor bus to Hampton Court.
对了 那正是你住的地方吧 说得没错吧？
Well, that's where you live, isn't it?
真是无礼
What impertinence.
嘿 说说他又是从哪儿来的吧 你好像能预言的样子
Hey, tell him where he comes from, you wanna go fortune-telling.
切尔滕纳姆 [英格兰西南部城市]
Cheltenham,
哈罗 [伦敦市郊地名]
Harrow,
剑桥还有 呃 印度？
Cambridge and, uh, lndia?
极为正确
Quite right.
啊 他不是侦探 他就是个爱管闲事的
Blimey, he ain't a tec, he's a blooming busybody.
容我问一句 先生 你是靠在音乐厅里表演这个为生的吗？
lf l may ask, sir, do you do this sort of thing for a living at a music hall?
嗯 我也曾考虑过 说不定有一天我会的
Well, l have thought of it. Perhaps l will one day.
他才不是什么绅士 否则怎么会欺负一个可怜的女孩儿
He's no gentleman. He ain't, to interfere with a poor girl.
我能问一下 你是怎么做到的吗？
How do you do it, may I ask?
简单来说就是语音学 研究语音的科学
Simple phonetics. The science of speech.
那是我的专业 也是我的爱好
That's my profession. Also my hobby.
任何人都能通过口音辨认出一个人是爱尔兰人还是约克郡人
Anyone can spot an lrishman or a Yorkshireman by his brogue,
但是我可以将一个人的生活地点缩小到6英里的范围内
but l can place a man within six miles.
而在伦敦我可以缩小到2英里
l can place him within two miles in London.
有时甚至可以缩小到两条街
Sometimes within two streets.
真该为自己感到羞耻 懦夫
Ought to be ashamed of himself, unmanly coward.
靠这个也可以谋生吗？
ls there a living in that?
噢 是的 可以说过得还相当不错
Oh, yes, quite a fat one.
让他忙他自己的吧 别再缠着我这个可怜的女孩儿了
Let him mind his own business and leave a poor girl--
你这女人！马上停止发出这可憎的哭声
Woman! Cease this detestable boohooing instantly
要不就另外找个同情你的地方待着去
or else seek the shelter of some other place of worship.
只要我愿意 我有权待在这儿 跟你一样
l have a right to be here if l like, same as you.
发出这样叫人厌恶与不舒服噪音的女人
Woman who utters such disgusting and depressing noises
没有权利出现在任何地方 连活着的权利都没有
has no right to be anywhere. No right to live.
别忘了你是个有灵魂的人
Remember that you're a human being with a soul
上天让你能够开口说话
and the divine gift of articulate speech.
你的母语
That your native language
莎士比亚 米尔顿 还有圣经都是用的这种语言
is the language of Shakespeare and Milton and the Bible.
别坐在那儿像个多胆汁质的鸽子一样咕咕咕的
Don't sit there crooning like a bilious pigeon.
啊噢！
Ow!
看看她 她是个生活在贫民区的人
[SINGlNG] Look at her A prisoner of the gutters
她嘴里发出的每一个音节都可以让你断定
Condemned by every syllable She utters
照律她应该被拖出去绞死
By right She should be taken out and hung
因为她冷血无情的谋杀了英语
For the cold-blooded murder Of the English tongue
啊噢！
Ow!
天哪！这是什么声音啊！
Heavens! What a sound!
这就是英国人 所谓的基础教育
This is what the British population Calls an elementary education.
噢 先生 我想你只是不幸挑错了例子
Come, sir, l think you picked a poor example.
是吗？
Did l?
听听这些站在苏豪广场的人们 [苏豪广场 伦敦苏豪区的一个广场]
[SINGlNG] Hear them down in Soho Square
全都不发H音
Dropping H's everywhere
英语任由他们喜欢怎么说都行
Speaking English any way they like
嘿 这位先生 你有上过学吗？
Hey, you, sir, did you go to school?
你把我 登 什么 傻瓜吗？
What do you take me for, a fool?
噢 没人教过他“当”该怎么念 可不是念“登”
Well, no one taught him "take" lnstead of "tike"
听听约克郡人 或者更糟糕的是 听听康沃尔郡的人的谈话吧
Hear a Yorkshireman, or worse Hear a Cornishman converse
我宁愿去听唱诗班
l'd rather hear a choir singing flat
就像一群鸡 在谷仓里咯咯叫 就像这个人一样
Chickens, cackling in a barn Just like this one
继续说
Garn.
“继续说”
"Garn."
请问 先生 你说刚才的那是什么词儿？
l ask you, sir, what sort of word is that?
就是“啊噢”和“继续说”连在一起 这就是为什么她只能生活在贫民区里
lt's "ow" and "garn" That keep her in her place
并非是由于她穿着破旧的衣服 以及满是污垢的面容
Not her wretched clothes And dirty face
为什么英国人 就不知道教会自己的孩子该怎么说英语呢？
Why can't the English Teach their children how to speak?
语言也分阶级 虽到如今 有些过时了
This verbal class distinction By now, should be antique
如果您也像她那样说话 先生 您也会过得跟她一样的
lf you spoke as she does, sir lnstead of the way you do
于是 您现在可能也是个卖花儿的
Why, you might be selling flowers too
请原谅
PlCKERlNG: l beg your pardon.
从一个英国人说话的方式 就能断定他是什么档次的人
An Englishman's way of speaking Absolutely classifies him
当他说话的时候
The moment he talks
便已经让其他英国人开始鄙弃他
He makes some other Englishman Despise him
我恐怕我们再也不会有一种同样的语言
One common language l'm afraid we'll never get
噢 为什么英国人就是不能
Oh, why can't the English learn to
向那些英语说得刺痛你耳朵的人们做个好榜样
Set a good example to people Whose English is painful to your ears
要换做是苏格兰人还有爱尔兰人说的话 简直叫人想哭
The Scotch and the lrish Leave you close to tears
甚至在有些地方 英语已经彻底的不复存在了
There even are places Where English completely disappears
因为 在美国 他们好多年前说的就不是英语了
Why, in America They haven't used it for years
[PICKERlNG LAUGHS]
为什么英国人 就不知道教会自己的孩子该怎么说英语呢？
Why can't the English Teach their children how to speak?
挪威人学挪威语 希腊人教自己后代说希腊语
Norwegians learn Norwegian The Greeks are taught their Greek
在法国每个法国人都背得出 法语的字母表
In France every Frenchman knows His language from A to Z
法国人事实上根本就不担心该怎么教
The French don't care what they do actually,
只要能正确发音就行
as long as they pronounce it properly.
阿拉伯人学阿拉伯语 就如同夏日的闪电一般快
[SINGlNG] Arabians learn Arabian With the speed of summer lightning
希伯来人几乎是令人恐怖的倒着学希伯来语 [希伯来语从右至左书写]
The Hebrews learn it backwards Which is absolutely frightening
说着正统英语 你却被当做怪人
Use proper English You're regarded as a freak
噢 为什么英国人...
Oh, why can't the English...
为什么英国人 就是不好好学该怎么说英语？
Why can't the English Learn to speak?
谢谢
Thank you.
你看见这个人 还有她那拙劣的英语了吗？
You see this creature with her curbstone English?
这样的英语不只会让她到死都生活在贫民区吗？
The English that'll keep her in the gutter till the end of her days?
这样吧 先生 在6个月之内 我会把她变得
Well, sir, in six months, l could pass her off
像一位公爵夫人一般出现在大使招待舞会上
as a duchess at an Embassy Ball.
我甚至可以让她得到一份工作 比如作一位小姐的侍女或是商店店员
l could even get her a job as a lady's maid or a shop assistant,
这些需要英语说得更好的工作
which requires better English.
喂 你在说什么？
Here, what's that you say?
噢 你这匹烂菜叶
Yes, you squashed cabbage leaf.
你简直是玷污了这些高贵的塔式建筑
You disgrace to the noble architecture of these columns.
你就是英语耻辱的化身
You incarnate insult to the English language,
我要把你变得如同希巴女王一样高贵 [希巴女王 一位阿拉伯半岛的女王 因敬慕所罗门王 与其生下一子]
l could pass you off as the Queen of Sheba.
[HlGGINS CHUCKLES]
噢 你也不相信他说的吧 上校
Oh, you don't believe that, captain.
一切皆有可能
Anything's possible.
我自己也在学习印度的土语
l myself am a student of lndian dialects.
是吗？
Are you?
你听说过皮克林上校吗 的作者？
Do you know Colonel Pickering, the author of Spoken Sanskrit?
我就是皮克林上校 你是哪位？
l am Colonel Pickering. Who are you?
我是亨利 希金斯 的作者
l'm Henry Higgins, author of Higgins Universal Alphabet.
我特意从印度来拜访你
l came from India to meet you.
我也打算去印度拜访你的
l was going to lndia to meet you.
- 希金斯 - 皮克林
- Higgins. - Pickering.
[BOTH LAUGHlNG]
- 希金斯 - 你住在什么地方？
PlCKERlNG: Higgins. - Where are you staying?
卡尔顿
At the Carlton.
不行 你怎么能住那里 你还是搬到温珀街27A号来吧
No, you're not. You're staying at 27A Wimpole Street.
跟我一起住 晚上用餐的时候我们可以好好聊聊
You come with me. We'll have a little jaw over supper.
- 说的没错 - 印度土语一直都很让我着迷
- Right you are. - Indian dialects always fascinated me.
好心的先生 买束花儿吧 我得用来付房租呢
Buy a flower, kind sir. l'm short for me lodgings.
撒谎
Liar.
你说过你可以找开半克朗的
You said you could change half a crown.
你这嘴里应该塞满钉子
You ought to be stuffed with nails, you ought.
给你 这篮子里所有的花儿都给你 只要6便士 [这里边几乎就没有花儿啊 赫本您这就是敲诈啊!]
Here, take the whole blooming basket for sixpence.
真是不依不饶
HlGGlNS: A reminder.
到底有多少种？
How many are there actually?
你问什么有多少种？
PlCKERlNG: How many what?
印度土语
HlGGlNS: lndian dialects.
不会少于
PlCKERlNG: No fewer than 147 distinct languages
印度官方记录的147种
are recorded as vernacular in lndia.
噢
Ow.
啊
Ah.
我们不该起身致意一下吗 先生们？
MAN 1 : Shouldn't we stand up, gentlemen?
一位妙龄的女士来到了我们中间
We've got a blooming heiress in our midst.
你不一直想找个好管家吗 伊莱莎？
Would you be looking for a good butler, Eliza?
噢 你不行
Well, you won't do.
这城里太无趣了 我想我得去趟巴黎
[SINGlNG] It's rather dull in town l think l'll take me to Paris
太太想去位于卡布里的城堡
The missus wants to open up The castle in Capri
我的私人医生建议我到海边避暑
Me doctor recommends A quiet summer by the sea
[CHORUS HUMMlNG]
这样的生活难道不惬意吗？
CHORUS [SINGlNG]: Wouldn't it be loverly
你今年打算去哪儿 伊莱莎？比亚里茨？ [比亚里茨 法国西南部城市]
Where you bound for this year, Eliza? Biarritz?
[MEN LAUGHlNG]
我所想要的只是一个这样的房间
[SINGlNG] All l want is a room somewhere
夜里没有冷风侵袭
Far away from the cold night air
有一张大椅子
With one enormous chair
噢 这样的生活难道不惬意吗？
Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
有好多的巧克力在等着我吃
Lots of chocolate for me to eat
炉子也烧得暖暖的
Lots of coal makin' lots of heat
温暖了我的脸 我的手 直到我的脚
Warm face, warm hands, warm feet
噢 这样的生活难道不惬意吗？
Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
噢 如此惬意的坐在 这般温暖的房间里直到
Oh, so loverly sittin' Abso-bloomin'-lutely still
直到春季来临前我甚至都不会挪动一下 趴在窗台上
l would never budge till spring Crept over the windowsill
心爱的人将头枕在我的膝上
Someone's head restin' on my knee
尽其所能的温柔的
Warm and tender as he can be
庇护着我
Who takes good care of me
噢 这样的生活难道不惬意吗？
Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
惬意 当然惬意
Loverly, loverly
多么惬意啊！
我所想要的只是一个这样的房间
CHORUS: All l want is a room somewhere
夜里没有冷风侵袭
Far away from the cold night air
里边有张大椅子
With one enormous chair
噢 这样的生活难道不惬意吗？
Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
有好多的巧克力在等着我吃
Lots of chocolate for me to eat
炉子也烧得暖暖的
Lots of coal makin' lots of heat
温暖了我的脸 我的手 直到我的脚
Warm face, warm hands, warm feet
噢 这样的生活难道不惬意吗？
Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
噢 如此惬意的坐在 这般温暖的房间里直到
Oh, so loverly sittin' Abso-bloomin'-lutely still
直到春季来临前我甚至都不会挪动一下 趴在窗台上
l would never budge till spring Crept over the windowsill
心爱的人将头枕在我的膝上
CHORUS: Someone's head restin' on my knee
尽其所能的温柔的
Warm and tender as he can be
庇护着我
Who takes good care of me
噢 这样的生活难道不惬意吗？
Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
惬意
CHORUS: Loverly
当然惬意
Loverly
多么惬意啊！
CHORUS: Loverly
[CHORUS WHlSTLlNG]
[ALL LAUGHlNG]
噢 这样的生活难道不惬意吗？ [呵呵 译者看到这里想笑]
Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
惬意
CHORUS: Loverly
当然惬意
Loverly
多么惬意啊！
CHORUS: Loverly
这样的生活难道不惬意吗？
Wouldn't it be loverly?
快走 阿尔菲 我们回去吧 这地方让我感觉很不好
JAMlE: Come on, Alfie, let's go home now. This place is giving me the willies.
回去？你这么急着回去干什么？
Home? What do you want to go home for?
快到5:00了
lt's nearly 5:00.
我女儿伊莱莎就快回来了
My daughter, Eliza, will be along soon.
她应该对得起
She ought to be good for a half a crown
疼爱她的老爸给她的半个克朗
for a father what loves her.
疼爱她？真是笑话
Loves her? That's a laugh.
你都多少个月没见过她了
You ain't been near her for months.
那又怎么样？
What's that got to do with it?
除了我给过她半克朗
What's half a crown after all l've give her?
你什么时候给过她什么东西？
When did you ever give her anything?
什么东西？我把一切都给了她
Anything? l give her everything.
我给了她作为一个人所能给出的最贵重的礼物
l give her the greatest gift any human being can give to another.
那就是生命
Life.
是我用奇迹将她带到这个世上 是我
l introduced her to this here planet, l did, with all its wonders and marvels.
阳光照耀着她 月光滋养着她
The sun that shines, the moon that glows.
让她可以在春日的夜晚下穿过海德公园
Hyde Park to walk through on a fine spring night.
在最繁华的城市伦敦里
The whole ruddy city of London
四处售卖她的鲜花儿
to roam around in, selling her blooming flowers.
这些都是我给她的
l give her all that.
然后我默默离开 让她独自享受这一切
Then l disappears and leaves her on her own to enjoy it.
要是这样都值不了半个克朗
Now, if that ain't worth half a crown now and again,
我就抽出腰里的皮带好好教训她
l'll take my belt off and give her what for.
你心肠真好 阿尔菲
You got a good heart, Alfie.
不过要要想从伊莱莎那儿要回那半个克朗的话
But you want that half a crown out of Eliza,
你最好编个更好的故事
you better have a good story to go with it.
就放心交给我吧 老弟
ALFlE: Leave that to me, my boy.
早上好 乔治
Good morning, George.
一个子儿都没有
Not a brass farthing.
早上好 阿尔基农
ALFlE: Good morning to you, Algernon.
一个子儿都没有
Not a brass farthing.
请进吧 请进
MAN 1 : Move on, please. Come on.
把你那肮脏的屁股从这里滚出去
Get your moving ass out of here.
带着它滚
On with it.
卖蔬菜 卖蔬菜了
MAN 2: Veggies. Get your veggies.
我们来了 新鲜的各种蔬菜
Here we are. Nice salad greens.
新鲜的西班牙洋葱
MAN 3: Lovely Spanish onion...
5镑...
MAN 4: Five pounds...
这确实是 新鲜的蔬菜
MAN 2: This is it. Nice bunches of veggies.
- 随便选 - 她在那儿
- Take your pick. - There she is.
都来看啊 西红柿 菜园里新鲜的西红柿
MAN 5: Tomatoes over here. Nice garden tomatoes.
红得诱人啊
WOMAN: Very tempting.
噢 伊莱莎 没想到在这儿碰见你
Why, Eliza, what a surprise.
一边去吧 查理 你对我来说太老了
Hop along, Charlie, you're too old for me.
- 你连谁是你女儿都认不出来了么？ - 那你要怎么才能找到她
- Don't know your own daughter? - How you gonna find her
- 你不会认为她长得像我吧？ - 我知道她的样子 走吧
- if you don't know what she looks like? - I know her. Come on.
我会找到她的
l'll find her.
伊莱莎 没想到在这儿碰见你
Eliza, what a surprise.
一个子儿都没有
Not a brass farthing.
噢 过来 伊莱莎
Here, you come here, Eliza.
我不会把自己辛苦挣来的钱
l ain't gonna take me hard-earned wages
给你拿去让该死的酒馆老板赚走的
and let you pass them on to a bloody pub keeper.
伊莱莎 你怎么忍心把我赶回你继母那里去
Eliza, you wouldn't have the heart to send me home to your stepmother
她连一滴酒都不给我 你就忍心吗？
without a drop of liquid protection, now, would you?
继母 是啊
Stepmother indeed.
噢 我愿意同她结婚
Well, l'm willing to marry her.
那是我自找的 我简直就是那个女人的奴隶 伊莱莎
lt's me that suffers by it. l'm a slave to that woman, Eliza.
就因为我不是他的合法丈夫
Just because I ain't her lawful husband.
别这样 给你老爸半克朗我就回去了
Come on, slip your old dad just half a crown to go home on.
嗯 昨晚我运气还不错
Well, l had a bit of luck myself last night.
是吗？
Yeah?
给你
So here.
不过以后别来缠着我要什么半克朗了
But don't keep coming around counting on half crowns from me.
谢谢 伊莱莎
Thank you, Eliza.
你真是个孝顺的女儿
You're a noble daughter.
啤酒 啤酒 金光闪闪的啤酒
[SINGlNG] Beer, beer, glorious beer
好好喝个饱
Fill yourself right up
你知道她是从哪儿来的吗？
WOMAN 1 : Do you know where she's been?
当然 我认识她 韦恩一直在打听她
WOMAN 2: Yeah, l know. Wayne is always asking.
[CHATTERlNG]
就是那个 意大利人
That one, Ginny.
别来烦我
WOMAN 3: Leave me alone.
[CHATTERlNG]
你看见这个人 还有她那拙劣的英语了吗？
HlGGlNS: You see this creature with her curbstone English?
这样的英语不只会让她到死都生活在贫民区吗？
The English that will keep her in the gutter till the end of her days?
这样吧 先生 在6个月之内 我会把她变得 像一位公爵夫人一般出现在大使招待舞会上
ln six months, l could pass her off as a duchess at an Embassy Ball.
我甚至可以让她得到一份工作 比如作一位小姐的侍女或是商店店员
l could even get her a job as a lady's maid or a shop assistant,
这些需要英语说得更好的工作
which requires better English.
你简直是玷污了这些高贵的塔式建筑
HlGGlNS: You disgrace to the noble architecture of these columns.
我甚至可以让她得到一份工作 比如作一位小姐的侍女或是商店店员
l could even get her a job as a lady's maid or a shop assistant,
这些需要英语说得更好的工作
which requires better English.
[TUNlNG FORK HUMMlNG]
A.
E. U. A...
[HUMMlNG VOWELS]
现在说说 你刚才听到的元音一共有多少个？
Now, how many vowel sounds do you think you heard altogether?
我想有24个
l believe l counted 24.
- 差了100多 - 什么？
- Wrong by a hundred. - What?
准确的说 你刚才听到的里边有130个元音
To be exact, you heard 1 30.
现在 再听一遍
Now, listen to them one at a time.
一定要这样吗？我已经听了有一上午了
Must l? l'm really quite done up for one morning.
[HlGGINS HUMMlNG VOWELS ON RECORDlNG]
请问芳名 请问小姐您的芳名
Your name, please. Your name, miss.
我的名字跟你有什么关系
My name is of no concern to you whatsoever.
请等一下
One moment, please.
噢 伦敦现在真是越来越脏了
Oh, London is getting so dirty these days.
我是皮尔斯太太 是这儿的管家 有什么需要我效劳吗？
PEARCE: l'm Mrs. Pearce, the housekeeper. Can l help you?
噢 早安 太太
Oh, good morning, missus.
麻烦让我见下教授
l'd like to see the professor, please.
你能告诉我找他有什么事吗？
Could you tell me what it's about?
- 是有关个人的事 - 噢
- It's business of a personal nature. - Oh.
请稍等
One moment, please.
[HlGGINS HUMMlNG VOWELS ON RECORDlNG]
希金斯先生？
Mr. Higgins.
什么事 皮尔斯太太？
What is it, Mrs. Pearce?
有位年轻的女士想要见您 先生
There's a young woman who wants to see you, sir.
年轻的女士？
A young woman?
她找我有什么事？
What does she want?
一位很寻常的女孩儿 先生 就是看上去很普通的那种
She's quite a common girl, sir. Very common indeed.
我本该让她离开的
l should have sent her away,
不过我想到也许你会想要把她的声音录下来
only l thought perhaps you wanted her to talk into your machine.
- 她的口音很有意思吗？ - 简直就是可怕 希金斯先生
- Has she an interesting accent? - Simply ghastly, Mr. Higgins.
很好 让她进来 让她进来吧 皮尔斯太太
Good. Let's have her in. Show her in, Mrs. Pearce.
那太好了 先生 很高兴听到您这么说
Very well, sir. lt's for you to say.
你真是走运 我让你看看是怎么录音的
This is rather a bit of luck. l'll show you how l make records.
我们让她说话 先把声音通过贝尔发明的声谱仪上
We'll set her talking and then l'll take her down first in Bell's Visible Speech,
转成波形图 然后我们就能通过留声机听到她的声音
then in Broad Romic, and then we'll get her on the phonograph
这样任何时候你想听她的声音都可以了
so that you can turn her on whenever you want
只要有了这张波形图
with the written transcript before you.
就是这位女士 先生
This is the young woman, sir.
早上好 尊敬的先生
Good morning, my good man.
我能有幸和您面对面的说上一句话吗？
Might l have the pleasure of a word with you face-to-face?
噢 不 不 不 这个女孩儿我昨天晚上就记录过了
Oh, no, no, no. This is the girl l jotted down last night.
她对我已经没用了 我已经得到了想要的关于里森 格鲁夫一带方言的所有记录
She's no use. l've got all the records l want of the Lisson Grove lingo.
我可不想在她身上再浪费一个录音筒了
l'm not gonna waste another cylinder on that.
现在 你请出去吧 我不想见到你
Now, be off with you. l don't want you.
别那么无礼 你都还不知道我为什么来呢
Don't be so saucy. You ain't heard what l come for yet.
你没告诉他我是乘出租车来的吗？
Did you tell him l come in a taxi?
别说这些了 女孩儿
Nonsense, girl.
你认为像希金斯先生这样的绅士会在意你是怎么来的吗？
What do you think a gentleman like Mr. Higgins cares what you came in?
噢 我们都是有自尊心的
Oh, we are proud.
噢 他不打算给教我了 他反悔了
Well, he ain't above giving lessons. Not him.
他之前说要教我的
l heard him say so.
好吧 我可不是来这儿 听你们说这些客气话的
Well, l ain't come here to ask for any compliment,
要不是因为我的钱不够的话 我也不会来这儿
and if my money's not good enough, l can go elsewhere.
不够什么？
Good enough for what?
付你的还是够了
Good enough for you.
现在 你明白了吗？我是来学习的 听清楚了
Now you know, don't you? l'm come to have lessons, l am.
我还会付学费 别搞错了
And to pay for them too. Make no mistake.
噢...
Well...
你希望我怎么回答你？
And what do you expect me to say?
好吧 如果你还算是位绅士的话 我想 你该先请我坐下
Well, if you was a gentleman, you might ask me to sit down, l think.
我不是说过了吗 我是来照顾你生意的？
Don't l tell you l'm bringing you business?
皮克林 我们是该请这个货物进来坐下
Pickering, should we ask this baggage to sit down
还是把她从窗户扔出去呢？
or shall we just throw her out of the window?
啊噢！我可不叫什么货物
Ow! l won't be called a baggage.
何况我还像任何一位女士那样要付给你学费
Not when I've offered to pay like any lady.
你为什么要这样做呢 小姑娘？
PlCKERlNG: What do you want, my girl?
我...我希望自己能像一位女士一样在花店里工作
l-- l want to be a lady in a flower shop
而不是在托特纳姆考特路的街角卖花
instead of selling at the corner of Tottenham Court Road.
但除非我说话能更有教养些 否则他们是不会要我的
But they won't take me unless l can talk more genteel.
他说过他会教我 所以 我就来了
He said he could teach me. Well, here I am.
我准备付钱给他 也不要他白教我
Ready to pay him, not asking any favor.
可他却当我是垃圾一样的对待我
And he treats me as if l was dirt.
我知道你上课收多少钱 我愿意掏钱
l know what lessons cost as well as you do, and l'm ready to pay.
付多少钱？
How much?
现在你说话了
Now you're talking.
趁还可以反悔 我想你还是别吹牛了
l thought you'd come off it when you saw a chance of getting back
昨天晚上你那样作践我
a bit of what you chucked at me.
- 你现在有一位客人 不是吗 嗯？ - 坐下吧
- You'd had a drop in, hadn't you, eh? - Sit down.
如果你打算为此道歉的话...
lf you're going to make a compliment of it--
坐下！
Sit down!
坐下 丫头 照我说的做
Sit down, girl. Do as you're told.
你叫什么名字？
What's your name?
伊莱莎 杜利特
Eliza Doolittle.
你能坐下吗 杜利特小姐？
Won't you sit down, Miss Doolittle?
噢
Oh.
我当然会不介意
l don't mind if l do.
说说吧 你打算为接受这些课程付我多少钱？
Now, how much do you propose to pay me for these lessons?
嗯 我是知道行情的
Oh, l know what's right.
我的一位女士的朋友上法语课的花费是一小时18便士
A lady friend of mine gets French lessons for 1 8 pence an hour
是由一位真正的法国绅士教的
from a real French gentleman.
噢 就凭你总不好意思也要收一样的价钱吧
Well, you wouldn't have the face to ask me the same
只不过教我自己的母语 就收我学法语的价钱
for teaching me my own language as you would for French.
所以我最多出1个先令
So l won't give more than a shilling.
随便你要不要
Take it or leave it.
你知道吗 皮克林 如果你不把1先令仅仅当做1先令来看
Do you know, Pickering, if you think of a shilling not as a simple shilling
而是从这个女孩儿的收入百分比来看
but as a percentage of this girl's income,
这几乎相当于
it works out as fully equivalent
一位百万富翁拿出了60到70镑
of 60 or 70 pounds from a millionaire.
以圣乔治名起誓 这太多了 这是我收的最多的一次
By George, it's enormous. lt's the biggest offer l ever had.
60镑？
Sixty pounds?
你们在说什么？我上哪儿能弄来60镑？
What are you talking about? Where would l get 60 pounds?
我根本没说过要付你60镑
l never offered you 60 pounds.
- 把嘴闭上 - 可我根本没有60镑
- Hold your tongue. - But l ain't got 60 pounds.
别哭了 傻丫头
Don't cry, you silly girl.
坐下吧 没人想碰你的钱
Sit down. Nobody's going to touch your money.
要是你还是继续痛哭流涕个没完
Somebody's going to touch you with a broomstick
有人就要用笤帚打你了 坐下！
if you don't stop sniveling. Sit down!
[STOPS CRYlNG]
噢 不知道的还以为你是我父亲
Oh, anybody would think you was my father.
要是我真要教你 我会比两个爸爸还要厉害
lf l decide to teach you, l'll be worse than two fathers to you.
[ELlZA SNlFFLES]
给你
Here.
- 给我这个干嘛？ - 擦擦眼泪吧
- What's this for? - To wipe your eyes.
把脸上弄湿了的地方都擦擦吧
To wipe any part of your face that feels moist.
记住 这就是你的手绢而这就是你的袖子
And remember, that's your handkerchief and that's your sleeve.
别把它们搞混了
And don't confuse the one with the other
要是你想成为一名女店员的话
if you want to become a lady in a shop.
您跟她那样讲没用 希金斯先生
lt's no use to talk to her like that, Mr. Higgins.
她根本不明白你在说什么
She doesn't understand you.
- 噢 把手绢给我 - 这手绢是他给我的 不是你
Here, give the handkerchief to me. He give it to me, not to you.
希金斯 我很好奇
Higgins, l'm interested.
你夸口说你能让她变得像公爵夫人一般
What about your boast that you could pass her off as a duchess
出席大使招待舞会 嗯？
at the Embassy Ball, eh?
如果你真能办到 我得说你就是这个世界上最伟大的老师
l'll say you're the greatest teacher alive if you can make that good.
我打赌你办不到 否则这个试验的所有的费用由我承担
l'll bet you all the expenses of the experiment that you can't do it.
甚至连她的学费我也一并支付
l'll even pay for the lessons.
噢 您真好 谢谢您 上校
Oh, you're real good. Thank you, captain.
要知道 这赌注很难拒绝
You know, it's almost irresistible.
她的品味如此低俗
She's so deliciously low.
如此肮脏可怖
So horribly dirty.
我才不脏
l ain't dirty.
我来之前洗过脸还有手 真的
l washed my face and hands before l come, l did.
我愿意同您打这个赌
l'll take it.
我会将她从贫民区的邋遢女孩儿变为一位公爵夫人
l'll make a duchess of this draggle-tailed guttersnipe.
今天就开始 现在 此时此刻起 皮尔斯太太 带她出去把她弄干净
We'll start today. Now. This moment. Take her away and clean her.
要是洗不掉的就用砂纸
Sandpaper if it won't come off any other way.
- 现在厨房里还有火吗？ - 是的 不过...
- Is there a good fire in the kitchen? - Yes, but--
把她所有的衣服都拿去 烧了 给她订做新的
Take all her clothes, burn them, and order new ones.
在新衣服送来之前先用牛皮纸把她裹起来
Just wrap her in brown paper till they come.
你这样太不绅士了 你怎么能这样说话
You're no gentleman. You're not to talk of such things.
我可是个品行端正的女孩儿 我是认真的
l'm a good girl, I am.
我也知道你是什么样的人 真的
And l know what the likes of you are, l do.
你这种贫民区出来的人用不着在我们面前装什么矜持 年轻的小姐
We want none of your slum prudery here, young woman.
你只要学会让自己的举止像一位公爵夫人就可以了
You've got to learn to behave like a duchess.
现在带她出去 皮尔斯太太
Now take her away, Mrs. Pearce.
要是她跟你捣乱的话 你就好好教训她
lf she gives you any trouble, wallop her.
我会叫警察的 我发誓
l'll call the police, l will.
我没地方让她住
l've got no place to put her.
- 这样吧 让她住在垃圾箱里 - 啊噢!
- Well, put her in the dustbin. - Ow!
别这样 希金斯 你这样太不近情理了
Come, Higgins, be reasonable.
你必须合乎情理一点儿 希金斯先生 我说真的
You must be reasonable, Mr. Higgins, really, you must.
你不可以像这样作践别人
You can't walk over everybody like this.
我吗？
l?
我有作践别人？
Walk over everybody?
我亲爱的皮尔斯太太 还有我亲爱的皮克林
My dear Mrs. Pearce, my dear Pickering.
我从没想过要作践谁
l had no intention of walking over anybody.
我只是觉得我们应该对这个可怜的姑娘更好一点
l merely suggested we should be kind to this poor girl.
我表达得不太清楚
l didn't express myself clearly
因为我不希望不符合她的品味
because l didn't wish to hurt her delicacy.
或者是你们的
Or yours.
可是 先生 您不能就这样把一个女孩儿带回来
But, sir, you can't take a girl up like that
就好像你在海滩上捡了块石头一样
as if you were picking up a pebble on the beach.
为什么不行？
Why not?
因为您一点都不了解她
But you don't know anything about her.
她的父母呢？她说不定已经结婚了
What about her parents? She may be married.
接着说
Garn.
看呐 要是这个女孩儿能正确的说出“说下去”
There. As the girl very properly says, "Garn."
有谁会和我结婚？
Who'd marry me?
我以圣乔治之名起誓 伊莱莎
By George, Eliza.
大街上会布满了因你而自杀的男人们的尸体
The streets will be strewn with the bodies of men
在我将你重新打造之前
shooting themselves for your sake before l'm done with you.
听着 我要离开这儿
Here. l'm going.
他在说胡话 绝对是这样
He's off his chump, he is.
- 我可不想让这样的蠢货教我 - 噢 疯子 我是吗？
- I don't want no barmies teaching me. - Oh, mad, am l?
那好 皮尔斯太太 别打电话订什么新衣服了
All right, don't ring up and order those clothes.
- 把她扔出去 - 不 希金斯先生 我可不能这样做
- Throw her out. - Stop, Mr. Higgins, l won't allow it.
回家去找你父母吧 丫头
Go home to your parents.
我没有父母
l ain't got no parents.
你听见了吧 她没有父母
There you are. She ain't got no parents.
有什么好奇怪的？没人会想要她
What's all the fuss? Nobody wants her.
她对任何人都是废物 除了我 带她上楼去
She's no use to anybody but me. Take her upstairs.
您打算拿她怎么办？让她做什么活儿付给她钱吗？
But what's to become of her? ls she to be paid anything?
噢 麻烦您理智一点儿 先生
Oh, do be sensible, sir.
她要钱干什么？她有的吃穿就够了
What would she do with money? She'll have food and clothes.
要是你给她钱 她就只会拿去喝酒
She'll only drink if you give her money.
噢 你真是个畜生 这是在胡说
Oh, you are a brute. It's a lie.
从来就没人见过我喝酒
Nobody ever saw the sign of liquor on me.
噢 先生 您是位绅士 求您让他别这样说我
Oh, sir, you're a gentleman. Don't let him speak to me like that.
你有没有想过希金斯 这个女孩儿也是有感情的？
Does it occur to you, Higgins, the girl has some feelings?
噢 不 我没想过 我们可不用担心她的感受
Oh, no, l don't think so. No feelings we need worry about.
嗯 你有吗 伊莱莎？
Well, have you, Eliza?
我同任何人一样有自己的感情
l got my feelings same as anyone else.
希金斯先生 我想我必须得知道这个女孩儿在这儿要待多久
Mr. Higgins, l must know on what terms the girl is to be here.
等你教完她 要拿她怎么办？
What's to become of her when you've finished your teaching?
您必须得看得更远一点儿 先生
You must look ahead a little, sir.
要是我们把她送回贫民区会怎样 皮尔斯太太？
What's to become of her if we leave her in the gutter?
- 请回答我 皮尔斯太太 - 那是她自己的事 用不着你管
- Answer me that, Mrs. Pearce. - That's her own business, not yours.
等我把她教完 我们就把她扔回去 之后就是她自己的事了
When l'm done, we'll throw her back, then it will be her own business again.
这样就没问题了吧 不是吗？
That will be all right, won't it?
你根本就没有同情心
You've no feeling heart in you.
你除了你自己什么都不关心
You don't care for nothing but yourself.
我受够了 我现在就要走 我是认真的
l've had enough of this. l'm going, l am.
你该为自己感到羞耻
You ought to be ashamed of yourself, you ought.
吃点儿巧克力吧 伊莱莎
Have some chocolates, Eliza.
我怎么知道这里边都放了什么？
How do l know what might be in them?
我听说有女孩儿被像你这样的人下了药
l've heard of girls being drugged by the likes of you.
为表示我的善意
Pledge of good faith.
我吃一半
l'll take one half
你吃另外一半
and you take the other.
你可以得到很多盒的巧克力 每天都你都会得到好几筒
You'll have boxes of them, barrels of them every day.
你可以拿它们当饭吃 嗯？
You'll live on them, eh?
我并不想吃 只是出于淑女的礼貌
l wouldn't have ate it, only l'm too ladylike
所以才没把它吐出来
to take it out of my mouth.
想想吧 伊莱莎
Think of it, Eliza.
想想巧克力 出租车还有黄金和钻石
Think of chocolates and taxis and gold and diamonds.
啊噢！我可不想要什么黄金还有钻石
Ow! l don't want no gold and no diamonds.
我可是个品行端正的女孩儿 我是认真的
l'm a good girl, I am.
希金斯 看来我必须介入 皮尔斯太太是对的
Higgins, l really must interfere. Mrs. Pearce is quite right.
要是让这个女孩儿在你手里待上6个月
lf this girl's gonna put herself in your hands for six months
进行所谓的教学试验
for an experiment in teaching,
她必须清楚的知道自己是在做什么
she must understand thoroughly what she's doing.
嗯
HlGGlNS: Mm.
伊莱莎 今后的6个月你将待在这儿
Eliza, you are to stay here for the next six months
学习如何像一位花店店员一样拥有美丽的谈吐
learning how to speak beautifully, like a lady in a florist shop.
如果你有好好做的话
lf you're good and do whatever you're told,
你就能睡在卧室里 还能得到很多好吃的
you shall sleep in a proper bedroom, have lots to eat
还会给你钱去买巧克力 让你出入都乘坐出租车
and money to buy chocolates and take rides in taxis.
但要是你不听话偷懒的话
But if you are naughty and idle,
你就得跟厨房里的黑蟑螂们睡在一起
you shall sleep in the back kitchen amongst the black beetles
还要被皮尔斯太太用笤帚打
and be walloped by Mrs. Pearce with a broomstick.
6个月之后
At the end of six months,
你将被带到白金汉宫
you shall be taken to Buckingham Palace
坐在车里 打扮得漂漂亮亮的
in a carriage, beautifully dressed.
要是被国王发现你不是个淑女
lf the king finds out that you're not a lady,
警察就会把你关进伦敦塔
the police will take you to the Tower of London
在那里砍掉你的脑袋
where your head will be cut off
以警告其他自以为是的卖花儿女孩儿
as a warning to other presumptuous flower girls.
但要是你没被揭穿 你就会得到
But if you are not found out, you shall have a present
7镑6先令的奖金并成为一名女店员
of seven and six to start life with as a lady in a shop.
要是你决绝这个提议
lf you refuse this offer,
你无疑就是最不领情的 坏女孩儿
you will be the most ungrateful, wicked girl
连天使都要为你落泪
and the angels will weep for you.
现在你满意了吧 皮克林？
Now, are you satisfied, Pickering?
我不明白你在说什么
l don't understand what you're talking about.
噢 我还要怎样解释才能让她明白 皮尔斯太太？
Oh, could l put it more plainly or fairly, Mrs. Pearce?
跟我来吧 伊莱莎
Come with me, Eliza.
没错 皮尔斯太太 就那样把她拖到浴室去
That's right, Mrs. Pearce. Bundle her off to the bathroom.
你真是太欺负人了
You're a great bully, you are.
要是我不愿意我就会离开这儿 我才不要让别人打我
l won't stay here if l don't like it. l won't let nobody wallop me.
别顶嘴 丫头
Don't answer back, girl.
我要是不知道自己是为什么来的 我才不会来这儿呢
ELlZA: lf l'd known what l was letting myself in for, l wouldn't have come here.
我一直都是个品行端正的女孩儿 我才 我才不会被你骗呢
l've always been a good girl, l am, and I won't be put upon.
在6个月内
ln six months--
如果她有一双好耳朵还有一根灵巧的舌头 甚至只要3个月就行
ln three if she has a good ear and a quick tongue.
我要带她去任何地方 让她扮谁都行
--l'll take her anywhere and l'll pass her off as anything.
我能将这个不幸的野丫头变成一位王后
l'll make a queen of that barbarous wretch.
[WATER RUNNlNG]
我这辈子都没有洗过澡
ELlZA: l've never had a bath in my life.
现在你可以真正的洗一回了
Not what you'd call a proper one.
要知道 如果你仪表不干净的话 你也不可能成为一位有内涵的好女孩儿
You know, you can't be a nice girl inside if you're dirty outside.
你就住这儿 这里就是你的卧室
l'll have to put you in here. This will be your bedroom.
噢 我可不能睡在这儿 太太 这儿对我这样的人来说太好了
Oh, l couldn't sleep here, missus. lt's too good for the likes of me.
这儿的东西我敢都不敢碰
l should be afraid to touch anything.
我现在还不是公爵夫人呢 你知道吗？
l ain't a duchess yet, you know?
噢 这是什么 这是你们洗衣服的地方吗？
Oh, what's this? This where you wash clothes?
这是我们自己洗澡的地方 伊莱莎
This is where we wash ourselves, Eliza.
现在我正要给你洗澡
And where l'm going to wash you.
你打算让我进那里边 然后把我弄得全身湿透？
You expect me to get into that and wet myself all over?
我不要
Not me.
我宁可死
l shall catch my death.
过来
Come along now.
过来吧 把身上的衣服脱掉
Come along. Take your clothes off.
别磨蹭了 丫头 听话 把衣服脱掉
Come on, girl, do as you're told. Take your clothes off.
- 快来 帮我把这些拿掉 - 啊噢！不 我不要
- Here, come on, help me take these. - Ow! No, l won't.
- 都过来帮忙 - 不 我不要
PEARCE: Come out of that. - No, l won't.
- 都来帮忙啊 - 不！
PEARCE: Everyone. - No!
我不要 把你们的手拿开
l won't. Take your hands off me.
- 不要 噢 我的天
- No. PEARCE: Oh, dear.
不 啊噢！
No. Ow!
- 不 我不要洗澡 让我走 伊莱莎 别动
- No, l won't. Let go. PEARCE: Eliza, keep still.
[ELlZA CRYlNG]
[CRYING]
- 就洗个澡 - 不
PEARCE: Take a bath. - No!
不要！
No!
我是个品行端正的女孩儿 我是认真的
l'm a good girl, I am.
噢 要是你不洗澡的话 他们不会喜欢你身上的味道的
PEARCE: Well, they won't like the smell of you if you don't have a bath.
这不行 这太不像话了
ELlZA: lt ain't right. lt ain't decent.
别拿走我的外套
Let go of my coat.
[ELlZA SCREAMlNG]
把你的手拿开
ELlZA: Take your hands off me.
过来吧
PEARCE: Come here.
- 不 - 我不会伤害你的
ELlZA: No. PEARCE: l won't hurt you.
让我走
ELlZA: Let me go.
放手
Take your hands off me.
我是个品行端正的女孩儿 我是认真的
l'm a good girl, I am.
我说了 放手
Take your hands off me, you hear.
伊莱莎 我不会放手的
PEARCE: Eliza, l won't have it.
我不会伤害你的
l wouldn't hurt you.
希金斯 恕我无礼
Higgins, forgive the bluntness,
既然我也参与此事 我认为自己应该对这个姑娘负责
but if l'm to be in this business, l shall feel responsible for the girl.
我希望你清楚不能
l hope it's clearly understood that no advantage
占她任何便宜
is to be taken of her position.
什么 那种事？好吧 我可以向你保证
What, that thing? Sacred, l assure you.
拜托 希金斯 你明白我的意思
Come now, Higgins, you know what l mean.
这可不是什么小事儿
This is no trifling matter.
对女人们而言你是一个有着良好品行的男人吧？
Are you a man of good character where women are concerned?
你有见过对女人们而言
Have you ever met a man of good character
品行良好的男人吗？
where women are concerned?
是的 那太常见了
Yes, very frequently.
噢 我可没见过
Well, l haven't.
我发现 只要我一旦同一位女人做朋友
l find the moment l let a woman make friends with me,
她就开始变得嫉妒 刻薄 多疑 极其惹人讨厌
she becomes jealous, exacting, suspicious and a damned nuisance.
此外我还发现 只要我一旦同一位女人做朋友
And l find the moment that l make friends with a woman,
我就开始变得自私且专横
l become selfish and tyrannical.
这就是为什么 我至今仍坚持单身的缘故
So here l am, a confirmed old bachelor and likely to remain so.
噢 毕竟 皮克林 我不过是这样一个男人
[SINGING] Well, after all, Pickering I'm an ordinary man
我所要的不多 只想能
Who desires nothing more Than just an ordinary chance
按照自己喜欢的方式生活 做那些自己喜欢的事
To live exactly as he likes And do precisely what he wants
我不过是个普通的男人 没有什么奇怪的想法
An average man am l Of no eccentric whim
只想过自己的生活 与世无争
Who likes to live his life Free of strife
做自己喜欢的事 就是他最想要的
Doing whatever he thinks ls best for him
噢 只不过是这样一个男人
Well, just an ordinary man
可要是让一个女人走进了你的生活 你平静的生活便被打破
But let a woman in your life And your serenity is through
她会重新布置你的家 从地下室直到屋顶
She'll redecorate your home From the cellar to the dome
然后继续开着迷人的玩笑 把你彻底的改造一遍
Then go on to the enthralling fun Of overhauling you
让一个女人走进你的生活 你等于自己面向了一堵高墙
Let a woman in your life And you're up against a wall
当你做好了打算之后 却发现她另有别的想法
Make a plan and you will find She has something else in mind
总不能什么都不做吧 于是你只能作别的
And so rather than do either You do something else
你根本就不喜欢的事情
That neither likes at all
你想聊聊基茨或是米尔顿 她却只想听你说你爱她
You want to talk of Keats or Milton She only wants to talk of love
你想去看场演出或是芭蕾 可她却整晚都忙着找手套
You go to see a play or ballet And spend it searching for her glove
让一个女人走进你的生活 你等于收到了永远争吵的请柬
Let a woman in your life And you invite eternal strife
让他们买结婚戒指 去给那些焦急盼望结婚的年轻女孩儿的小手带上吧
Let them buy their wedding bands For those anxious little hands
我宁愿让 牙医在我的牙齿上钻孔
I'd be equally as willing For a dentist to be drilling
也好过让一个女人走进自己的生活
Than to ever let a woman in my life
我是一个非常温和的人 平和而温厚
I'm a very gentle man Even-tempered and good-natured
从不惹人抱怨
Who you never hear complain
全身每根血管都 充满着人情味
Who has the milk of human kindness By the quart in every vein
我是个有耐心的男人 从头到脚
A patient man am I Down to my fingertips
我是那种永远不可能 也不会
The sort who never could Ever would
轻易出言冒犯
Let an insulting remark escape his lips
的非常温和的男人
A very gentle man
可要是让一个女人走进你的生活 耐心也就不复存在
But let a woman in your life And patience hasn't got a chance
她虽然会征求你的意见 你的回答即便简短
She will beg you for advice Your reply will be concise
她也会听得很认真
And she'll listen very nicely
可回头 就照着自己的想法乱来
Then go out And do precisely what she wants
你本是一个优雅光鲜的男人 总是细语轻声
You are a man of grace and polish Who never spoke above a hush
可如今突然从你嘴里说出的话 简直能够让水手都感到脸红
Now all at once you're using language That would make a sailor blush
让一个女人走进你的生活 就等于在自己身上插了一把刀
Let a woman in your life And you're plunging in a knife
让其他的男人们 往自己的脖子上套上婚姻的枷锁吧
Let the others of my sex Tie the knot around their necks
我宁愿接受 西班牙宗教裁判所新式的酷刑
l'd prefer a new edition Of the Spanish lnquisition
也好过让一个女人走进自己的生活
Than to ever let a woman in my life
我是一个安宁生活的男人
l'm a quiet-living man
喜欢静静的躺在自己的卧室里 度过漫漫长夜
Who prefers to spend the evenings ln the silence of his room
喜欢如同未被发现的坟墓一般 安详的气氛
Who likes an atmosphere as restful As an undiscovered tomb
我是一个爱沉思的男人 喜欢享受哲学的乐趣
A pensive man am l Of philosophic joys
喜欢冥想 沉思
Who likes to meditate, contemplate
远离俗世的疯狂 与非人的嘈杂
Free from humanity's mad lnhuman noise
一个安宁生活的男人
A quiet living man
可要是让一个女人走进你的生活 你就等于永无假期
But let a woman in your life And your sabbatical is through
她的朋友们如同一支 没有尽头的军队源源不断
ln a line that never ends Come an army of her friends
前来同她叽叽喳喳喋喋不休
Come to jabber and to chatter
跟她说 你在外边又怎么了
And to tell her what the matter Is with you
她有一个庞大 而喧闹的家族
She'll have a booming Boisterous family
挤到你面前 只想知道谁会继承你的遗产
Who will descend On you en masse
她会有一个说话声音大得像唱瓦格纳歌剧的母亲 随便一声就能把玻璃都震碎
She'll have a large Wagnerian mother With a voice that shatters glass
让一个女人走进你的生活
Let a woman in your life
[RECORDED VOlCE PLAYlNG ON FAST-FORWARD]
让一个女人走进你的生活
Let a woman in your life
[RECORDED VOlCE PLAYlNG ON FAST-FORWARD]
[RECORDED VOlCES STOP]
我永远都不会让一个女人走进我的生活
l shall never let a woman in my life
滚出去
MAN: Get out of here.
杰米 你们也滚出去
The two of you get out too.
得了吧 杜利特
Come on, Doolittle.
记住 想喝酒就得付钱
And remember, drinks are to be paid for or not drunk.
谢谢你的招待 乔治
Thanks for your hospitality, George.
把帐单送到白金汉宫吧 走吧
Send the bill to Buckingham Palace. Come on.
好了 阿尔菲 继续留在这儿也没什么用了 我想该回去干活儿了
Well, Alfie, there's nothing else to do. l guess it's back to work.
什么？
What?
你最好别在我面前提那个词儿
Don't you dare mention that word in my presence again.
瞧瞧这些可怜的笨蛋
Look at all these poor blighters down here.
[LAUGHS]
我以前做那个 只不过是为了运动一下
l used to do that sort of thing once, just for exercise.
那可不值得 让你花上一整天的时间
lt's not worth it. Takes up your whole day.
噢 别担心 伙计们 我们很快就不会这样了
Oh, don't worry, boys. We'll get out of this somehow.
你准备怎么办 阿尔菲？
How do you think you're going to do that, Alfie?
怎么办？跟从前一样
How? Same as always.
信心 希望再加上一点好运
Faith, hope and a little bit of luck.
主赋予了男人 一双钢铁般的臂膀
[SINGlNG] The Lord above gave man An arm of iron
让他可以去做自己的工作 不知疲倦
So he could do his job And never shirk
主赋予了男人 一双钢铁般的臂膀 不过
The Lord above gave man An arm of iron but
只要一点点的好运 只要一点点的好运
With a little bit of luck With a little bit of luck
别人就会去做 那些不值得去做的工作
Someone else'll do The blinkin' work
只要一点点 只要一点点
With a little bit With a little bit
只要一点点的好运 你就永远都不需要工作
ALL [SlNGlNG]: With a little bit ofluck You'll never work
主创造了酒 作为诱惑
The Lord above made liquor For temptation
以察视男人是否能远离 罪恶
To see if man could turn away From sin
主创造了酒 作为诱惑 不过
The Lord above made liquor For temptation but
只要一点点的好运 只要一点点的好运
With a little bit of luck With a little bit of luck
当诱惑来临 你便立即屈服
When temptation comes You'll give right in
只要一点点 只要一点点
With a little bit With a little bit
只要一点点的好运 你便立即屈服
With a little bit of luck You'll give right in
噢 你可以选择走 大道或是小路
Oh, you can walk The straight and narrow
但只要一点点的好运 你就会胡作非为
But with a little bit of luck You'll run amuck
女人 是神创造给男人结合的
The gentle sex Was made for man to marry
与他共同生活 替他做饭
To share his nest And see his food is cooked
女人 是神创造给男人结合的 不过
The gentle sex Was made for man to marry but
只要一点点的好运 只要一点点的好运
With a little bit of luck With a little bit of luck
你就能拥有一切 却不必被婚姻束缚
You can have it all And not get hooked
只要一点点 只要一点点
With a little bit With a little bit
只要一点点的好运 你就不必被婚姻束缚
With a little bit of luck You won't get hooked
只要一点点 只要一点点
With a little bit With a little bit
只要一点点天赐的好运
With a little bit of bloomin' luck
人们总会 朝你扔东西
They're always throwin' Goodness at you
不过只要一点点的好运 就可以躲开
But with a little bit of luck A man can duck
主创造男人 去帮助他的邻居
The Lord above made man To help his neighbor
不论什么地方 在陆地 在海中 或是在云里
No matter where On land, or sea, or foam
主创造男人 去帮助他的邻居 不过
The Lord above made man To help his neighbor but
只要一点点的好运 只要一点点的好运
With a little bit of luck With a little bit of luck
当他来找你的时候 你正好不在家
When he comes around You won't be home
只要一点点 只要一点点
With a little bit With a little bit
[BAND PLAYlNG]
只要一点点的好运 你正好不在家
With a little bit of luck You won't be home
只要一点点 只要一点点
With a little bit With a little bit
只要一点点天赐的好运
With a little bit of bloomin' luck
你是个妇女参政运动的支持者 阿尔菲
HARRY: You make a good suffragette, Alfie.
噢 干你自己该干的去吧
MAN: Oh, get along with you.
噢 那个走运的家伙又来了
Why, there's the lucky man now.
尊贵的阿尔菲 杜利特
The Honorable Alfie Doolittle.
你在伊莱莎的屋里做什么？
What are you doing in Eliza's house?
她以前住这儿
Her former residence.
你现在可以自己买酒了 阿尔菲 杜利特
You can buy your own drinks now, Alfie Doolittle.
你可真是掉进黄油桶里了
Fallen into a tub of butter, you have.
- 你在说什么？ - 你女儿 伊莱莎
- What are you talking about? - Your daughter, Eliza.
你真走运 阿尔菲 杜利特
You're a lucky man, Alfie Doolittle.
嗯 伊莱莎怎么了？
Well, what about Eliza?
噢！他还不知道呢 她自己的父亲都还不知道
Oh! He don't know. Her own father and he don't know.
[PEOPLE LAUGHlNG]
伊莱莎穿得漂漂亮亮的回来过一次
Moved in with a swell, Eliza has.
然后又自己乘计程车走了 就同画里一样时髦
Left here in a taxi all by herself, smart as paint.
- 之后三天都没回家了 - 接着说
- And ain't been home for three days. - Go on.
直到今天早上我才收到她的一封信
Then this morning, l get a message from her.
她要把她的东西全都送到
She wants her things sent over.
温珀街27A号
To 27A Wimpole Street,
由希金斯教授转交...
care of Professor Higgins.
[HOPKlNS LAUGH]
- 想知道她都要搬走什么东西？ - 都什么？
- And what things does she want? - What?
她的鸟笼和中国折扇
Her birdcage and her Chinese fan.
[ALFlE LAUGHS]
“不过”她在信里说
"But," she says,
“衣物什么的就不必送过来了”
"never mind about sending any clothes."
[ALL LAUGHlNG]
我早就知道她有出息
l knew she had a career in front of her.
哈利老弟 我们得一起庆祝下
Harry boy, we're in for a booze-up.
这回阿尔弗雷德 P 杜利特可走运了 [阿尔菲是阿尔弗雷德的简称]
The sun is shining on Alfred P. Doolittle.
男人被造出来 是为了供养自己的孩子的
[SINGlNG] A man was made To help support his children
这是 天经地义的事情
Which is the right And proper thing to do
男人被造出来 是为了供养自己的孩子的 不过
A man was made To help support his children but
只要一点点的好运 只要一点点的好运
With a little bit of luck With a little bit of luck
他们就会反过来 开始供养你
They'll go out And start supporting you
只要一点点 只要一点点
With a little bit With a little bit
只要一点点的好运 他们就会替你工作
With a little bit of luck They'll work for you
只要一点点 只要一点点
With a little bit With a little bit
只要一点点天赐的好运
With a little bit of bloomin' luck
[BAND PLAYlNG]
噢 男人外出风流 是个罪过
Oh, it's a crime For man to go philanderin'
会让自己妻子那可怜的心 充满忧伤与怀疑
And fill his wife's poor heart With grief and doubt
噢 男人外出风流 是个罪过 不过
Oh, it's a crime For a man to go philanderin' but
只要一点点的好运 只要一点点的好运
With a little bit of luck With a little bit of luck
你会发现 即便是猎犬也嗅不到
You can see The bloodhound don't find out
只要一点点 只要一点点
With a little bit With a little bit
只要一点点的好运 她就不会发现
With a little bit of luck She won't find out
查理 过来 只要一点点
MAN: Charlie, over here. - With a little bit
只要一点点
With a little bit
只要一点点天赐的好运
With a little bit of bloomin' luck
您的信 先生
The mail, sir.
是账单的话就付钱 是邀请函的话就推掉
Pay the bills and say no to the invitations.
A
ELlZA: A.
A.
[SNEEZES]
A
A.
A!
您不能再这样训练那丫头了
You simply cannot go on working the girl this way.
让她翻来覆去的念字母表
Making her say her alphabet over and over
从太阳升起直到落下 甚至吃饭的时候都不停
from sunup to sundown, even during meals.
您这样会把自己累坏的 要什么时候才能结束啊？
You'll exhaust yourself. When will it stop?
当然直到她能正确念出来为止
When she does it properly, of course.
还有什么吗 皮尔斯太太?
ls that all, Mrs. Pearce?
这里还有一封信
There's another letter
是那个名叫厄斯拉 D 瓦林福德的美国富翁寄来的
from that American millionaire, Ezra D. Wallingford.
他是希望你能去他的 道德重塑社团 做演讲
He still wants you to lecture for his Moral Reform League.
噢 好吧 把它扔掉
Yes, well, throw it away.
这是他写给您的第三封信了
lt's the third letter he's written you, sir.
- 您总得给个答复吧 - 好吧
- You should at least answer it. - All right.
把它放在桌子上吧 皮尔斯太太 我会试着给他回信的
Leave it on the desk, Mrs. Pearce. l'll try and get to it.
如果您愿意的话 先生 楼下有一位清洁工
lf you please, sir, there's a dustman downstairs,
自称阿尔弗雷德 P 杜利特 想要见您
Alfred P. Doolittle, who wants to see you.
他说她女儿在您这儿
He says you have his daughter here.
我早就跟你说过
PlCKERlNG: l say.
嗯 让那个无赖上来
Well, send the blackguard up.
他也许不是个无赖 希金斯
PlCKERlNG: He may not be a blackguard, Higgins.
胡说 他当然是个无赖 皮克林
Nonsense. Of course he's a blackguard, Pickering.
不管他是不是 我恐怕他会给我们找麻烦的
Whether he is or not, l'm afraid we'll have some trouble with him.
不 我不这么认为
No, l think not.
即便有什么麻烦 那也是我找他麻烦 而不是他找我
Any trouble to be had, he'll have it with me, not l with him.
杜利特到了 先生
Doolittle, sir.
希金斯教授？
Professor Higgins?
过来吧
HlGGlNS: Here.
哪儿？
Where?
噢 早上好 先生
Oh, good morning, governor.
我来是为件非常重要的事的 先生
l come about a very serious matter, governor.
在豪恩斯洛长大
Brought up in Hounslow.
母亲是威尔士人 我想
Mother Welsh, l should think.
你想要什么 杜利特？
What is it you want, Doolittle?
我想要回我女儿 就是这样 明白了吗？
l want my daughter, that's what l want, you see?
嗯 当然是这样 你是她父亲 对吗？
Well, of course you do. You're her father, aren't you?
我很高兴看到你还有那么点儿亲情
l'm glad to see you have a spark of family feeling left.
她就在里边 好的 马上把她带走吧
She's in there. Yes, take her away at once.
什么？
What?
把她带走
Take her away.
你认为我会替你照看女儿吗？
Do you think l am going to keep your daughter for you?
噢 这样做合理吗 先生？
Now, is this reasonable, governor?
这样占别人便宜公平吗？
ls it fairity to take advantage of a man like that?
这个女孩儿是我的 你占有了她
The girl belongs to me. You got her.
我该怎么办？
Where do l come in?
你怎么胆敢上这儿勒索我
How dare you come here and attempt to blackmail me.
也许就是你故意把她送这儿来的
You sent her here on purpose.
噢 你怎么可以这样指控别人 先生
Now, don't take a man up like that, governor.
警察自然会指控你
The police shall take you up.
这是有预谋的 以威胁手段进行勒索的阴谋
This is a plan, a plot to extort money by threats.
我要打电话报警
l shall telephone the police.
我有问你要过一个子儿吗？
Have l asked you for a brass farthing?
让旁边的这位绅士来评评理 我哪怕有一个字提到钱了吗？
l'll leave it to this gentleman here. Have l said a word about money?
那你来是为什么？
What else did you come for?
嗯...
Well...
一个醉鬼来能为什么？
What would a bloke come for?
做人得讲道理 先生
Be human, governor.
[LAUGHS]
阿尔弗雷德 你是故意把她送到这儿来的
Alfred, you sent her here on purpose.
相信我 先生 我没有那样做
So help me, governor, l never did.
那你怎么知道她在这儿？
Then how did you know she was here?
我会告诉你的 先生 如果你能让我说的话
l'd tell you, governor, if you'd only let me get a word in.
我这就要告诉你 我正想要告诉你
l'm willing to tell you. l'm wanting to tell you.
我正迫不及待的要告诉你
l'm waiting to tell you.
你看 皮克林
You know, Pickering,
这家伙确实有点语言天赋
this chap's got a certain natural gift of rhetoric.
请注意他说话时如林中鸟叫般的节奏
Observe the rhythm of his native woodnotes wild.
“我这就要告诉你 我正想要告诉你
"l'm willing to tell you. l'm wanting to tell you.
我正迫不及待的要告诉你”这就是他变形的威尔士口音
l'm waiting to tell you." That's the Welsh strain in him.
要不是你把她送来的你怎么知道伊莱莎在这儿？
How did you know Eliza was here if you didn't send her?
嗯 她送信说要取走她的行李 我正好听说了
Well, she sent back for her luggage and l got to hear about it.
还说所有的衣服她都不要了
She said she didn't want no clothes.
听到这些我会怎么想 先生？
What was l to think from that, governor?
请问你 作为一位父亲 我会怎么想？
l ask you, as a parent, what was l to think?
那么你是来趁她还活着赶来救她的吗 嗯？
So you came here to rescue her from worse than death, eh?
没错 先生 正是这样
Just so, governor, that's right.
那好
Yes.
皮尔斯太太
Mrs. Pearce.
皮尔斯太太 伊莱莎的父亲要带她走了
Mrs. Pearce, Eliza's father has come to take her away.
把她交给他 好吗？
Give her to him, will you?
噢 等等 先生 等等
Now, wait a minute, governor, wait a minute.
你我都是男人 不是吗？
You and me is men of the world, ain't we?
噢 我们都是男人 不是吗？
Oh, men of the world, are we?
- 好吧 你先出去 皮尔斯太太 - 我确实也是那样想的 先生
- Yes, you better go, Mrs. Pearce. - I think so indeed, sir.
嘿 先生
Here, governor.
我本以为你是抱着某种想法
l've took a sort of a fancy to you and--
[LAUGHS]
如果你想要这个女孩儿 那好吧 我也就不坚持要把她带回去了
lf you want the girl, well, l ain't so set on having her back home again,
不过我还是得把话说清楚
but what l might be open to is an arrangement.
我所要求的不过是一位父亲正当的权利
All I ask is my rights as a father.
即便是这世上就你最后一个男人 您也不会指望我什么都不要就让她跟你走吧
You're the last man alive to expect me to let her go for nothing.
噢 我看得出您是那种正直的人 先生
Oh, l can see you're one of the straight sort, governor.
因此 您觉得5张1英镑的对您来说算什么？
So, what's a 5-pound note to you?
我的伊莱莎总值这个价吧？
And what's Eliza to me?
我想应该让你知道 杜利特
l think you ought to know, Doolittle,
这位希金斯先生把你女儿接到这里 用意是绝对高尚的
that Mr. Higgins' intentions are entirely honorable.
当然是这样 先生
Of course they are, governor.
要不是这样 我会要50镑的
lf l thought they wasn't, l'd ask 50.
你的意思是说你打算以50镑卖掉你的女儿？
Do you mean to say you'd sell your daughter for 50 pounds?
你连一点道德都没有吗 伙计？
Have you no morals, man?
不 不 我可买不起它们 先生
No, no, l can't afford them, governor.
要是您跟我一样穷 你也会这样的
Neither could you if you was as poor as me.
我想提醒你们 我并没有什么恶意
Not that l mean any harm, mind you.
但既然伊莱莎可以得到一些好处的话
But if Eliza is gonna have a bit out of this,
那我为什么不能呢 嗯？
why not me too, eh?
为什么不能呢？
Why not?
噢 从我的角度来看
Well, look at it my way.
我是什么？我问你 我是什么？
What am l? l ask you, what am l?
我是个不值得可怜的人 就是这样
l'm one of the undeserving poor, that's what l am.
现在 想想看这对一个男人意味着什么
Now, think what that means to a man.
这意味着他一生都要同中产阶级所谓的道德观对抗
lt means he's up against middle-class morality for all of time.
不论发生什么 我想要的就只是得到点儿好处
lf there's anything going and l puts in for a bit of it,
结果往往都是这样
it's always the same story.
“你不配接受救济 所以不会给你”
"You're undeserving so you can't have it."
可我真的需要 就如同那些最需要救济的寡妇一样
But my needs is as great as the most deserving widows
她们每周都能从6个不同的慈善团体得到救济金
that ever got money out of six different charities in one week
只因为死了同一个丈夫
for the death of the same husband.
我要的不应该比一个需要救济的人少 而是更多
l don't need less than a deserving man, l need more.
我吃得不比他少
l don't eat less hearty than he does.
此外我还要喝酒 很多的酒
And l drink, oh, a lot more.
我实话跟你说吧 我不是装作需要救济
l'm playing straight with you. l ain't pretending to be deserving.